Robert Broder Photographs and Papers, 1953-2013
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Robert Broder Photographs and Papers, 1953-2013
MS 551
Broder, Robert
Photographs and papers (1953-2013). This collection contains photographic prints, contact sheets, negatives, and slides created by Robert Broder while employed by the University of Arizona, the Tucson Citizen, and as a freelance photographer. Also included are newspapers and publications containing printed versions of Broder’s works, documents, correspondence, and photography course materials.
12.5 Linear feet; 25 boxes
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/ E-Mail: LBRY-askspcoll@email.arizona.edu
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Biographical Note
Robert Broder began his photography career as a member of the Tucson High School Camera Club in 1956, submitting numerous photographs to the school’s newspaper and various local publications. Between 1957-1973, he was staff photographer for the University of Arizona Photographic Department. The photographs he created in this position document student life, faculty, campus buildings, events-including a visit by Robert Kennedy in 1968, athletic competitions, and views of the campus. In 1962, while still in this position at the University of Arizona, he worked as staff photographer for the Hughes Aircraft Company in Tucson, AZ where he developed an expertise in industrial photography. In 1966, he accepted a part time staff photographer position at the Tucson Daily Citizen and also worked as a string photographer for various local newspapers and publications including the Arizona Republic. The photographs he created during this period document people and various events that occurred in the Tucson, Phoenix, and southern Arizona region. As an assignment for the Arizona Republic, he photographed the 1968 production of Lonesome Cowboys, a film directed by Andy Warhol that was shot at Old Tucson Studios. These photographs were later exhibited at a show in 2001 at the Etherton Gallery in Tucson, AZ and published in a corresponding book edited by Eric Kroll titled Warhol: Dylan to Duchamp (these materials are not held within this collection). In 1973, he was an instructor at the Winona School of Photography located in Winona Lake, Indiana. Beginning in 1980 he worked as a freelance photographer specializing in wedding and stock photography.
Throughout his career, Broder received several local and national photography awards and had his works exhibited in local, national, and international exhibits.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 8 series.
Series I: Prints, 1955-2010
Sub-Series 1: Personal and Professional Work, 1955-2010
Sub-Series 2: University of Arizona, 1955-2010
Series II: Slides, circa 1958-1995
Sub-Series 1: Personal and Professional Materials, circa 1958-1995
Sub-Series 2: University of Arizona circa 1958-1995
Series III: Negatives, circa 1958-1995
Series IV: Published Photographs, 1955-2011
Series V: Documents, 1953-2013
Series VI: Correspondence, 1954-2004
Series VII: Photography Course Materials, 1963
Series VIII: David Fitzsimmons Sketches, circa 1980-1991
Scope and Content Note
This collection has seven series and contains photographic materials and papers created by Robert Broder. Materials in this collection date from 1953-2013 and document the University of Arizona as well as people and events within the Tucson and Southern Arizona region.
The first series has two subseries and contains black and white and color prints of varying sizes and contact sheets. The first subseries contains materials that were published in regional newspapers and magazines, as well as materials that were entered into national and international photography competitions and exhibits and freelance work. These materials document events, photographic studies, animals, people, as well as personal photographs that were not intended for publishing or exhibit. These materials document personal friends and professional colleagues, and trips. The second subseries contains photographs that were published in the Arizona Daily Wildcat and local newspapers. The materials document athletic teams, internal and external views of campus buildings, prominent faculty and, Robert Kennedy’s visit in March, 1968, student life, and views of campus.
The second series has two subseries and contains slides. The first subseries has no arrangement and contains personal and professional materials created by Robert Broder. The second subseries has no arrangement and contains materials that document The University of Arizona including students, faculty, buildings, sporting events, campus views, and surrounding businesses.
The third series contains black and white and color negatives of various sizes with some materials duplicated in Series 1 and Series 2. The majority of the materials are held in their original housing and contain identification by the creator. A portion of the materials are unidentified. This series has no arrangement and is described at the box level.
The fourth series contains copies of newspapers, magazines, and other publications that published photographs by Robert Broder. The fifth series contains documents collected or created by Robert Broder. It consists of press passes issued to Broder, business cards, resumes, and various certificates and awards.
The sixth series contains correspondence primarily sent to Robert Broder. It consists of letters from editors of various publications concerning photographs Broder submitted for publication, exhibit submission and awarding, camera product suggestions, award letters, and letters of appreciation. Of particular interest are correspondence from Congressman Morris Udall, University of Arizona President Richard Harvill, and a photocopy of a letter sent by Andy Warhol.
The seventh series contains photography course materials. It consists of materials from The Gellert-Wolfman Publishing Corporation Photo Methods for Industry course in which Robert Broder was enrolled as well as materials from a course he taught at the Winona School of Photography in 1972.
The eight series contains sketches created by David Fitzsimmons, cartoonist for the Arizona Daily Star.
Access Terms
Adams, Ansel, 1902-1984.
Smith, W. Eugene, 1918-1978.
Warhol, Andy, 1928-1987.
University of Arizona – Buildings.
University of Arizona – Faculty.
University of Arizona – Pictorial works.
University of Arizona – Students.
Photojournalism – United States.
Tucson (Ariz.) -- Pictorial works.
Container List
- Series 1: Prints, 1955-2010
  This series has two subseries. It contains black and white and color prints of varying sizes and contact sheets.
  - Subseries 1: Personal and Professional Work, 1955-2010
    This series is described at the folder level and is arranged alphabetically by subject. It contains black and white and color prints that vary in size. The series contains materials that were published in regional newspapers and magazines, as well as materials that were entered into national and international photography competitions and exhibits. These materials document events; photographic studies; animals; people; celebrities and notable photographers, including Jane Goodall, Ansel Adams, and W. Eugene Smith; buildings; sporting events; athletic teams; self-portraits; and various locales within the Tucson, Arizona region. This series also contains personal photographs that were not intended for publishing or exhibit. These materials document personal friends and professional colleagues, and trips. Boxes 3 – 8 contains oversize prints, with the majority mounted. These materials have no arrangement and consist of prints of people, sporting events, locations, and views. Some of the materials are unique while some duplicate materials in boxes 1 and 2.
    - Ansel Adams, 1980 February (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Animals (1 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Animals (2 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Athletics, 1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Robert Broder, 1962-2010 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Buildings, circa 1960-2007 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Jane Goodall, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Las Vegas, Nevada, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Lodge on the Desert Wedding Party, circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Modern Furniture, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - People (1 of 2), circa 1955-2008 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - People (2 of 2), circa 1955-2008 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Old Tucson, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Photograph Album, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Pima Air and Space Museum, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Plants, Flowers, and Cacti, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Jack Scheaffer/Tucson Press Club Events (1 of 2), 1984, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Jack Sheaffer/Tucson Press Club Events (2 of 2), 1984, undated (Box 2A, Folder 1)
    - W. Eugene Smith, 1979 (Box 2A, Folder 2)
    - Views, 1971-2008 (Box 2A, Folder 3)
    - Oversize Prints (Box 3)
    - Oversize Prints (Box 4)
    - Oversize Prints (Box 5)
    - Oversize Prints (Box 6)
  - Subseries 2: University of Arizona, 1955-2010
    This series is described at the folder level and is arranged alphabetically by subject. It contains black and white and color prints that vary in size. The series contains materials that were published in various University of Arizona publications and local newspapers. The materials document athletic teams, internal and external views of buildings on campus – including the construction of the McKale Memorial Center circa 1972, prominent faculty from various colleges and staff including Dr. Gerard P. Kuiper, Dr. Bart J. Bok, Robert Kennedy’s visit in March, 1968, student life, and views of campus.
    - Animals, Department of Zoology, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Athletics, 1968-2005, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Buildings, circa 1965 (Box 7A, Folder 1)
    - Center for Creative Photography Dedication Ceremony, 1989 (Box 7A, Folder 2)
    - Faculty / Staff (1 of 2), 1965-1971 (Box 7A, Folder 3)
    - Faculty / Staff (2 of 2), 1965-1971 (Box 7A, Folder 4)
    - President Richard Harvill, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Robert Kennedy, 1968 March (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Students (1 of 2), 1963-2005 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Students (1 of 2), 1963-2005 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Views, circa 1965-2000 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Oversize Prints (Box 9)
    - Oversize Prints (Box 10)
- Series 2: Slides, 1958-1995
  This series has two subseries with materials described at the box level. The first subseries has no arrangement and contains personal and professional materials created by Robert Broder. The majority of materials are in color, with a small number of black and white materials present. Some of the professional materials were published in regional newspapers and publications and are duplicated in the first series. The second subseries has no arrangement and contains materials that document The University of Arizona including students, faculty, buildings, and surrounding businesses. The majority of materials are in color, with a small number of black and white materials present. Some of the materials were published in the Daily Wildcat as well as other regional newspapers and publications.
  - Subseries 1: Personal and Professional Materials, 1958-1995
    - Slides (Box 11)
    - Slides (Box 12)
    - Slides (Box 13)
    - Slides (Box 14)
    - Slides (Box 15)
    - Slides (Box 16)
  - Subseries 2: University of Arizona, circa 1958-1995
    - Slides (Box 17)
- Series 3: Negatives, circa 1958-1995
  This series has no arrangement and is described at the box level. It contains black and white and color negatives of various sizes with some materials duplicated in Series 1 and Series 2. The majority of the materials are held in their original housing and contain identification by the creator. A portion of the materials are unidentified.
  - Negatives (Box 18)
  - Negatives (Box 19)
  - Negatives (Box 20)
  - Negatives (Box 21)
  - Negatives (Box 22)
  - Negatives (Box 23)
  - Negatives (Box 24)
  - Negatives (Box 25)
  - Negatives (Box 26)
- Series 4: Published Photographs, 1955-2011
  This series contains copies of newspapers, magazines, and other publications including programs from Tucson High School and course guides for the Winona School of Professional Photography in which photographs by Robert Broder were published. These publications were printed primarily in the Tucson, AZ region. The photographs document a wide array of subjects, with some duplicated in Series 1, Series 2, and Series 3. Materials in box 24 are oversize.
  - Newspapers and publications, 1956-2011 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Newspapers (1 of 6), 1956-2011 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Newspapers (2 of 6), 1956-2011 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Newspapers (3 of 6), 1956-2011 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Newspapers (4 of 6), 1956-2011 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Newspapers (5 of 6), 1956-2011 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Newspapers (6 of 6), 1956-2011 (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Magazines and Publications (1 of 2), 1955-1988 (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - Magazines and Publications (2 of 2), 1955-1988 (Box 28, Folder 8)
- Series 5: Documents, 1953-2013
  This series contains documents collected or created by Robert Broder. It consists of press passes issued to Broder, business cards, resumes, and various certificated and awards.
  - Press Passes and Business Cards, 1956-1986, undated (Box 28, Folder 9)
  - Resumes, circa 1989, undated (Box 28, Folder 10)
  - Certificates and Awards, 1953-2013 (Box 28, Folder 11)
- Series 6: Correspondence, 1954-2004
  This series contains correspondence primarily sent to Robert Broder. It consists of letters from editors of various publications concerning photographs Broder submitted for publication, exhibit submission and awarding, camera product suggestions, award letters, and letters of appreciation. Of particular interest are correspondence from Congressman Morris Udall, Richard Harvill, and a photocopy of a letter sent by Andy Warhol.
  - Correspondence (1 of 2), 1954-2004 (Box 28, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence (2 of 2), 1954-2004 (Box 28, Folder 13)
- Series 7: Photography Course Materials, 1963-1965, 1972
  This series contains photography course materials. It consists of materials from The Gellert-Wolfman Publishing Corporation Photo Methods for Industry course in which Robert Broder was enrolled as well as materials from a course he taught at the Winona School of Photography in 1972.
  - The Gellert-Wolfman Publishing Corporation Photo Methods for Industry, 1963-1965 (Box 28, Folder 14)
  - Winona School of Photography, 1972 (Box 28, Folder 15)
- Series 8: David Fitzsimmons Sketches, circa 1980-1991
  This series contains sketches by David Fitzsimmons, cartoonist for the Arizona Daily Star. Some of the materials are inscribed to Robert Broder.
  - Sketches, circa 1980-1991 (Box 29)